<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology. for the Church of England, with relation to the spirit of persecution; for which she is accused</title>
            <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5762B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230169</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896208</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77890)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2382:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology. for the Church of England, with relation to the spirit of persecution; for which she is accused</title>
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Gilbert Burnet.</note>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured from Wing B5762A.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴</note>
                  <note>In this edition A1r first column last line has "Imputations" (roman), and the title has a period after "apology".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="apology">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153838:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY. For the CHURCH of ENGLAND, With relation to the Spirit of PERSECUTION; For which She is accuſed.</head>
            <p n="1">I. ONe should think, that the Behaviour of the <hi>Engliſh Clergy</hi> for ſome years paſt, and the preſent Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in which they are, should ſet them beyond <hi>Slander,</hi> and by conſequence above <hi>Apologies;</hi> yet ſince the the Malice of her Enemies works againſt her with ſo much <hi>ſpight,</hi> and ſince there is no Inſinuation that carrys ſo much Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice in it, and that ſeems to have ſuch co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of truth on it, as this of their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſet on a ſevere <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> of being ſtill ſour'd with that leaven, and of carrying the ſame Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable hatred to them, which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Reputation that they have gained, may put them in a further capacity of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting, if another revolution of affairs should again give them authority to ſet about it; it ſeems neceſſary to examin it, and that the rather, becauſe ſome aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate this ſo far, as if nothing were now to be ſo much dreaded as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi>'s getting out of her preſent di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</p>
            <p n="2">II. If theſe Imputations were charged on us only by thoſe of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> we should not much wonder at it; for tho it argues a good degree of Confidence, for any of that communion to declaim againſt the ſeverities that have been put in practice among us, ſince their <hi>little finger muſt be heavier than ever our loins</hi> were, and to whoſe <hi>Scorpions</hi> our <hi>Rods</hi> ought not to be compared; yet after all, we are ſo much accuſtomed to their methods, that nothing from them can ſurpriſe us To hear <hi>Papiſts</hi> declare againſt <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites</hi> cry up <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> are, we confeſs, unuſual things: yet there are ſome degrees of shame, over which when People are once paſſed, all things become ſo familiar to them, that they can no more be put out of countenance. But it ſeems very ſtrange to us, that <hi>ſome,</hi> who if they are to be believed, are ſtrict to the ſevereſt forms and ſubdiviſions of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> and who ſome years ago were jealous of the ſmalleſt ſteps that the <hi>Court</hi> made, when the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger was more remote, and who cried out <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Perſecution,</hi> when the deſign was ſo maskt that ſome welmeaning men
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:153838:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153838:3"/>could not miſs being deceived by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that were made, and the diſguiſes that were put on; that, I ſay, theſe very perſons who were formerly ſo diſtruſtful, should now, when the Mask is laid off, and the deſign is avowed, of a ſudden grow to be ſo <hi>belïeving,</hi> as to throw off all diſtruſt, and be ſo gulled as to betray all; and to expoſe us to the Rage of thoſe, who muſt needs give ſome good words, till they have gone the round, and tried how effectually they can divide and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, that ſo they may deſtroy us the more eaſily; this is indeed ſomewhat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary. They are not ſo Ignorant as not to know, that <hi>Popery</hi> cannot change its <hi>nature,</hi> and that <hi>Cruelty and Breach of Faith to Hereticks,</hi> are as neceſſary parts of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as <hi>Tranſubſtantiation and the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> are. If <hi>Papiſts</hi> were not Fools, they muſt give good Words and fair Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, till by theſe they have ſo far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded the poor credudous Hereticks, that they may put themſelves in a poſture to execute the Decrees of their Church againſt them: and tho we accuſe that Religion as guilty both of <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Treachery,</hi> yet we do not think them <hi>Fools:</hi> ſo till their Party is ſtronger than God be thanked it is at preſent, they can take no other method than that they take. The <hi>Church of England</hi> was the <hi>Word</hi> among them ſome years ago, <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> is the <hi>Word</hi> at preſent; and have all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible reaſon to aſſure us, that the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for maintaining the one, will be as religiouſly kept as we ſee thoſe are which were lately made with ſo great a profu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Proteſtations, and shews of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship for the ſupporting of the other.</p>
            <p n="3">III It were great Injuſtice to charge all the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> with the Impertinencies that have appeared in many <hi>Addreſſes</hi> of late, or to take our meaſures of them, from the Impudent ſtrains of an <hi>Alſop</hi> or a <hi>Care,</hi> or from the more Important and now more viſible ſteps that ſome among them, of a higher form, are every day making; and yet after all this, it cannot be denyed but the ſeveral bodies of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have behave themſelves of late like men, that underſtand too well the true Intereſt of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and of the <hi>English Government,</hi> to ſacrifice the whole and themſelves in Concluſion to their private reſentments I hope the ſame juſtice will be allowed me in ſtating the matter relating to the ſo much decried <hi>Perſecution,</hi> ſet on by the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and that I may be ſuffered to diſtinguish the heats of ſome angry and deluded men, from the Doctrine of the Church, and the practices that have been authoriſed in it; that ſo I may shew, that there is no reaſon to Infer from paſt errors, that we are Incurable; or that new Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities inviting us again into the ſame ſeverities, are like to prevail over us to commit the ſame follies over again. I will firſt ſtate what is paſt, with the ſincerity that becomes one that would not <hi>lye for God;</hi> that is, not affraid nor ashamed to confeſs faults, that will neither aggravate nor-extenuate them beyond what is juſt, and that yet will avoid the ſaying any thing that may give any cauſe of offence to any <hi>party</hi> in the Nation.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. I am very ſorry that I muſt confeſs, that all the parties among us, have shewed, that as their turn came to be upper moſt, they have forgot the ſame Principles of Moderation and Liberty which they all claimed when they were oppreſſed. If it should shew too much ill nature to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min what the <hi>Presbytery</hi> did in <hi>Scotland</hi> when the <hi>Covenant</hi> was in Dominion, or what the <hi>Independents</hi> have done in <hi>New-England,</hi> why may not I claim the ſame priviledge with relation to the <hi>Church of England,</hi> if ſeverities have been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by her while she bore rule? yet it were as eaſy as it would be invidious to shew, that both <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents</hi> have carried the principle of Rigour in the point of Conſcience much higher, and have acted more Implacably upon it than ever the <hi>Church of England</hi> has done, even in its angrieſt fits; ſo that none of them can much reproach another for their exceſſes in thoſe matters. And as of all the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153838:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Religions</hi> in the world the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is the moſt <hi>perſecuting,</hi> and the moſt bound by her Principles to be unalterably Cruel; ſo the <hi>Church of England</hi> is the leaſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting in her principles, and the leaſt obliged to repeat any errors to which the Intrigues of Courts or the Paſſions inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all parties may have engaged her, of any National <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Europe.</hi> It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be any part of our Doctrine, when we came out of one of the blackeſt <hi>Perſecutions</hi> that is in Hiſtory, I mean <hi>Q. Maryes,</hi> we shewed how little we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the Cruelty of that Church, which had provoked us ſo ſeverely; when not only no Inquiries were made into the illegal acts of Fury, that were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in that Perſecuting Reign, but even the Perſecutors themſelves lived among us at eaſe and in peace; and no <hi>Penal law</hi> was made except againſt the publick exerciſe of that Religion, till a great many Rebellions and Treaſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted them from us for our own preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. This is an Inſtance of the Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of our Church, that perhaps can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be matched in Hiſtory: and why should it not be ſuppoſed, that if God should again put us in the ſtate in which we were of late, that we should rather imitate ſo Noble a Pattern, than return to thoſe <hi>miſtakes</hi> of which we are now <hi>aſhamed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">V. It is to be conſidered, that upon the late <hi>Kings</hi> Reſtauration, the remembrance of the former <hi>War,</hi> the ill Uſage that our Clergy had met with in their <hi>Seque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations,</hi> the angry Reſentments of the <hi>Cavalier party,</hi> who were ruined by the <hi>War,</hi> the Intereſt of the <hi>Court</hi> to have all thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> condemned, that had occaſioned it, the heat that all <hi>parties</hi> that have been ill uſed are apt to fall into upon a <hi>Revolution;</hi> but above all, the practices of thoſe who have ſtill blown the Coals, and ſet us one againſt another, that ſo they might not only have a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded force to deal with, but might by turns make the <hi>Diviſions</hi> among us ſerve their <hi>Ends:</hi> all theſe, I ſay, concurred to make us loſe the happy opportunity that was offered in the year 1660. to have healed all our Diviſions, and to have triumphed over all the <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> not by ruining them, but by overcoming them with a ſpirit of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Gentleneſs;</hi> which is the only Victory that a generous and Chriſtian temper can deſire. In short, unhappy <hi>Councils</hi> were followed, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere <hi>Laws</hi> were made. But after all, it was the <hi>Court party</hi> that carried it for rougher methods: ſome conſiderable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, not neceſſary to be here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, as they ſtopped the mouths of ſome that had formed a wiſer Project, ſo they gave a fatal Advantage to angry and crafty men, that to our misfortune, had too great a ſtroak in the conduct of our affairs at that time. This ſpirit of Severity was heightned by the Practices of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> who engaged the late <hi>King</hi> in December 1662. to give a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi> Thoſe who knew the ſecret of his Religion, as they ſaw that it aimed at the Introduction of <hi>Popery,</hi> ſo they thought there was no way ſo effectual, for the keeping out of Popery, as the maintaining the <hi>Uniformity,</hi> and the ſuppreſſing of all deſigns for a <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> But while thoſe who managed this, uſed a due reſerve, in not diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſecret motive that led them to it, others flew into ſeverity, as the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in vogue: and thus all the ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the rigour of the Laws, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the firſt <hi>Dutch</hi> War, that were ſet on upon the pretence of quieting the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of encouraging Trade, were reſiſted by the Inſtruments of an honeſt <hi>Miniſter of State,</hi> who knew as well then, as we do now, what lay ſtill at bottom, when <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> was pretended.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Upon that Miniſters <hi>Diſgrace,</hi> ſome that ſaw but the half of the <hi>Secret,</hi> perceiving in the Court a great Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Toleration,</hi> and being willing to take meaſures quite different from thoſe of the former <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> they entred into a treaty for a <hi>Comprehenſion of-ſome Diſſenters, and the Tolerating of others;</hi> and ſome <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Clergymen,</hi> that were Inferiour to none
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:153838:4"/>of the Age in which they lived, for true Worth and a right Judgment of things, engaged ſo far, and with ſo much ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs into this project, that the matter ſeemed done, all things being concerted among ſome of the moſt conſiderable men of the different parties. But the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of that <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and the Jealouſy of the ill deſigns of the <hi>Court,</hi> gave ſo ſtrong a prejudice againſt this, that the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition could not be ſo much as hearkned to by the Houſe of Commons: and then it appeared how much the whole <hi>Popish Party</hi> was allarmed at the project: it is well known with how much Deteſtation they ſpeak of it to this day: tho we are now ſo fully ſatisfied of their Intentions to deſtroy us, that the Zeal which they pretended for us, in oppoſing that deſign, can no more paſs upon us.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. At laſt, in the year 1672. the deſign for <hi>Popery</hi> diſcovering it ſelf, the end that the <hi>Court</hi> had in favouring a <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration</hi> became more Viſible: and when the <hi>Parliament</hi> met, that condemned the <hi>Declaration for Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> the Members of the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> that either were <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> or that favoured them, behaved themſelves ſo worthily in concurring with thoſe of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> for ſtifling that <hi>Toleration,</hi> choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing rather to loſe the benefit of it, than to open a breach at which <hi>Popery</hi> should come in, that many of the <hi>members</hi> that were for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> promiſed to procure them a bill of <hi>Eaſe for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Diſſenters.</hi> But the <hi>Seſſion</hi> was not long enough for bringing that to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and all the Seſſions of that <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> after that, were ſpent in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſtrugle between the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi> party, that there was never room given for calm and wiſe Consultations: yet tho the <hi>Party</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> did not perform what had been promiſed by ſome Leading men to the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> there was little or nothing done againſt them, after that, till the year 1681. ſo that for about nine years together they had their Meetings almoſt as publickly and as regularly as the <hi>Church of England</hi> had their Churches, and in all that time; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever particular hardships any of them might have met with in ſome corners of <hi>England,</hi> it cannot be denied but they had the free Exerciſe of their Religion, at leaſt in moſt parts.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. In the year 1678. things began to change their face: it is known, that upon the breaking out of the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> the <hi>Clergy</hi> did Univerſally expreſs a great deſire for coming to ſome temper in the points of <hi>Conformity:</hi> all ſorts and ranks of the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſeemed to be ſo well diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed towards it, that if it had met with a ſuteable entertainment, matters might probably have been in a great meaſure compoſed. But the Jealouſy that thoſe who managed the Civil concerns of the Nation in the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> took off all that was done at <hi>Court,</hi> or propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by it, occaſioned a fatal breach in our publick Councils: in which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, the <hi>Clergy</hi> by their principles, and Intereſts, and their dispoſition to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve well of the <hi>Court,</hi> were determined to be of the Kings ſide. They thought it as a ſin to miſtruſt the late Kings <hi>Word,</hi> who aſſured them of his ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ſo often, that they firmly depended on it: and his preſent <hi>Majeſty</hi> gave them ſo many Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances of his <hi>maintaining</hi> ſtill the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that they believed him like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: and ſo thought that the Excluſion of him from the Crown, was a degree of rigour to which they in Conſcience could not conſent: upon which they were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally cried out on, as the Betrayers of the Nation and of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion:</hi> Thoſe who demanded the <hi>Excluſion,</hi> and ſome other ſecurities, to which the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops</hi> would not conſent in Parliament, looked on them as the chief hindrance that was in their way: and the Licence of the Preſs at that time was ſuch, that many Libels and ſome ſevere Diſcourses were published againſt them. Nor can it be denied, that many <hi>Churchmen,</hi> who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood not the Principles of Humane
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153838:4"/>Society, and the rules of our Government, ſo well as other points of Divinity, writ ſeveral Treatiſes concerning the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of ſubmiſſion, that were then as much cenſured, as their performances ſince againſt <hi>Popery</hi> have been deſervedly admired. All this gave ſuch a Jealouſy of them to the <hi>Nation,</hi> that it muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that the ſpirit which was then in fermentation when very high againſt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as a <hi>Confederate,</hi> at leaſt, to <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi> Nor were ſeveral of the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> wanting to Inflame this diſlike; all ſecret Propoſitions for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodating our differences were ſo cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained, that they were ſcarce heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to. The Propoſitions which an Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Divine</hi> made even in his books writ againſt <hi>Seperation,</hi> shewed, that while we maintained the War in the way of diſpute, yet we were ſtill willing to <hi>treat:</hi> for that <hi>Great man</hi> made not thoſe advances towards them without conſulting with his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. Yet we were then fatally given up to a ſpirit of Diſſention: and tho the <hi>Parliament</hi> in 1680. entred upon a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject for healing our differences, in which great ſteps were made to the removing of all the occaſions of our Conteſts; the <hi>Leaders</hi> of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> to the amaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all perſons, made no account of this: and even ſeemed uneaſy at it, of which the Earl of <hi>Nottingham</hi> and Sr. <hi>Thomas Clarges,</hi> that ſet on that Bill with much zeal, can give a more particular account. All theſe things concurred to make thoſe of the <hi>Church of England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, <hi>a little too rashly,</hi> that their ruin was reſolved on; and then it was no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if the ſpirit of a <hi>Party,</hi> the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the <hi>laſt Wars,</hi> the preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Danger,</hi> and above all, the great favour that was shewed them at <hi>Court,</hi> threw them <hi>fatally</hi> into ſome angry and Violent Counſels; ſelf-preſervation is very natural: and it is plain, that many of them took that to be the caſe; ſo that truly ſpeaking, it was not ſo much at firſt a ſpirit of Perſecution, as a deſire of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling thoſe who they believed intended to ruin them from effecting their deſigns, that ſet them on to all thoſe <hi>unhappy</hi> things that followed. They were animated to all they did by the <hi>continued</hi> earneſtneſs of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Duke,</hi> and of their <hi>Miniſters.</hi> That Reproach of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the <hi>Law,</hi> who is now ſo <hi>high,</hi> was ſingled out for no other end, but to be their <hi>Common Hangman</hi> over <hi>England:</hi> of whom the late <hi>King</hi> gave this true cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, <hi>That he had neither Wit, Law, nor Common Sence; but that he had the Impudence of ten carted Whores in him.</hi> Another <hi>Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foon,</hi> was hired to plague the Nation with three or four papers a week; which to the Reproach of the Age, in which we live, had but too great and too ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral an effect, for poyſoning the ſpirits of the <hi>Clergy.</hi> But thoſe who knew how all this was managed, ſaw that it was not only ſet on, but ſtill kept up by the <hi>Court.</hi> If any of the <hi>Clergy had</hi> but preached a word for moderation, he had a chiding ſent him preſently from the Court; and he was from that day marked out as a <hi>dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected perſon:</hi> and when the <hi>Clergy of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> did very worthily refuſe to give In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations againſt their parishioners that had not always conformed, the deſign ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been formed, upon that to bring them into the <hi>Spiritual Courts,</hi> and <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> them, and make them loſe their right of <hi>Voting,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Charter of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> might have been delivered up when ſo many <hi>Citizens</hi> were by ſuch means shut out of the <hi>Common Council;</hi> we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member well how ſeverely they were cenſured for this, by ſome that are now dead, and others that are yet alive. I will not go further into this matter: I will not deny but many of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were put to great hardships, in many parts of <hi>England.</hi> I cannot deny it, and I am ſure I will never juſtify it. But this I will poſitively ſay, having obſerved it all narrowly, that he muſt have the brow of a <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> that can cast this wholly on the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and free the <hi>Court</hi> of it. The beginnings and the progreſs of it came from the <hi>Court,</hi> and from the <hi>Popish party:</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153838:5"/>and tho perhaps every one does not know all the ſecrets of this matter, that others may have found out, yet no man was ſo Ignorant as not to ſee what was the chief ſpring of al thoſe Irregular motions that ſome of us made at that time: ſo upon the whole matter, all that can be made out of this, is, that the paſſions and Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of ſome of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> being unhappily ſtirred up by the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> they were fatally conducted by the <hi>Popish party,</hi> to be the Inſtruments in doing a great deal of miſchief.</p>
            <p n="9">IX. It is not to be doubted, but tho ſome weaker men of the <hi>Clergy</hi> may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſtill retain their little peevish ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, againſt the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> yet the wiſer and more ſerious heads of that great and <hi>Worthy body,</hi> ſee now their error: they ſee who drove them on in it, till they hoped to have ruined them but it. And as they have appeared againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> with as great a ſtrength of learning and of firm ſteadineſs as perhaps can be met with in all Church-Hiſtory, ſo it cannot be doubted, but their reflections on the dangers into which our Diviſions have thrown us, have given them truer No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with relation to a rigorous <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity:</hi> and that the juſt Deteſtation which they have expreſſed of the Corruptions of the <hi>Ch. of Rome,</hi> has led them to conſider and abhor one of the worſt things in it, I mean their <hi>Severity</hi> towards <hi>Hereticks.</hi> And the ill uſe that they ſee the <hi>Court</hi> has made of their zeal for ſupporting the Crown, to juſtify the ſubverſion of our Government that is now ſet on, from ſome of their large &amp; unwary expreſſions, will certainly make them hereafter more cautions in medling with <hi>Politicks:</hi> the <hi>Bishops</hi> have under their hands both diſowned that wide extent of the <hi>Prerogative,</hi> to the overturning of the <hi>Law,</hi> and declared their dispoſition to come to a <hi>Temper</hi> in the matters of <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> and there ſeems to be no doubt left of the ſincerity of their Intentions in that matter. Their Piety and Vertue, and the proſpect that they now have of ſuffering themſelves, put us beyond all doubt as to their ſincerity; and if ever God in his Providence brings us again into a ſetled State, out of the ſtorm into which our paſſions and folly, as well as the treachery of others has brought us, it cannot be imagined, that the <hi>Bishops</hi> will go off from thoſe moderate Reſolutions, which they have now declared: and they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing firm to them, the weak and Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet paſſions of any of the Inferiour <hi>Clergy,</hi> muſt needs vanish, when they are under the conduct of wiſe and worthy Leaders. And I will boldly ſay this, that if the <hi>Ch: of England,</hi> after she has got out of this ſtorm, will return to hearken to the peevishneſs of ſome <hi>ſour</hi> men, she will be abandoned both of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> and will ſet both <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> againſt her. The Nation ſees too Viſibly, how dear the dispute a bout <hi>Conformity</hi> has coſt us, to ſtand any more upon ſuch <hi>Punctilios:</hi> and THOSE <hi>in whom our deliverance is wrapt up,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this matter too well, and judge too right of it, to imagin that ever they will be <hi>Prieſtridden</hi> in this point. So that all conſiderations concur to make us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that there is no danger of our ſplit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a ſecond time upon the ſame rock: and indeed, if any Argument were wanting to compleat the certainty of this point, the wiſe and Generous behaviour of the main body of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Juncture, has given them ſo juſt a Title to our friendship, that we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to ſet all the world againſt us, if we can ever forget it; and if we do not make them all the returns of eaſe and favour when it is in our power to do it.</p>
            <p n="10">X. It is to be hoped, that when this is laid together, it will have that effect on all ſober and true <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as to make them forget the little angry Heats that have been among us, and even to forget the Injuries that have been done us: all that we do now one againſt another, is to shorten the work of our Enemies, by deſtroying one another, which muſt in Concluſion turn to all our <hi>Ruin.</hi> It is a madmans revenge, to deſtroy our Friends
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153838:5"/>that we may do a pleaſure to our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, upon their giving us ſome good words; and if the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> can truſt to <hi>Papiſts</hi> after the uſage that the <hi>Church of England</hi> has met with at their hands, all the comfort that they can promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, when <hi>Popery</hi> begins to act its natural part among us, and to ſet <hi>Smithfield</hi> again in a <hi>fire,</hi> is that which befell ſome <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> who were firſt put in the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> but were afterwards removed to <hi>Bedlam:</hi> ſo tho thoſe falſe Brethren among the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who deceive them at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, are certainly no <hi>Changlings,</hi> but know well what they are doing; yet thoſe who can be cheated by them, may well claim the Priviledge of a <hi>Bedlam,</hi> when their Folly has left them no other retreat.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. I will not digreſs too far from my preſent purpoſe; nor enter into a diſcuſſion of the <hi>Dispenſing power,</hi> which was ſo effectually overthrown the other day at the <hi>Kings Bench Bar,</hi> that I am ſure all the Authority of the <hi>Bench</hi> it ſelf is no more able to Support it: yet ſome late <hi>Papers</hi> in favour of it, give me occaſion to add a little relating to that point It is true, the Aſſertor of the <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing power,</hi> who as lately appeared <hi>with allowance,</hi> pretends, that it can only be applied to the <hi>Teſt</hi> for publick Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments: for he owns that the <hi>Teſt</hi> for both Houſes of Parliament is left en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, as not within the compaſs of this extent of the Prerogative: but another Writer, whom by his fence we muſt conclude an <hi>Irish man,</hi> by his brow a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> and by the bare deſignation in the title page, of <hi>James Stewarts letter,</hi> a <hi>Quaker,</hi> goes a ſtrain higher, and thinks the King is ſo abſolutely the Soveraign as to the Legiſlative part of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he may diſſolve even the <hi>Parliament Teſt:</hi> ſo nimbly has he leapt from being a <hi>Secretary to a Rebellion,</hi> to be an <hi>Advocate for Tyranny.</hi> He fancies that becauſe no <hi>Parliament</hi> can bind up another, therefore they cannot limit the <hi>Preliminarys</hi> to a ſubſequent Parliament. But upon what is it then, that <hi>Countyes</hi> have but two Knights, and <hi>Burroughs</hi> as many: that <hi>men</hi> below ſuch a value have no vote, that <hi>Sheriffs</hi> only receive Writs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn Elections, beſides many more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary requiſites to the making a legal Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. In short, if <hi>Laws</hi> do not regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Election and Conſtitution of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> all theſe things may be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, and the <hi>King</hi> may caſt the whole Government in a new Mould, as well as diſſolve the obligation that is on the <hi>Members</hi> of Parliament for taking the <hi>Teſt.</hi> It is true, that as ſoon as a Parliament is legally met and conſtituted, it is tyed by no Laws, ſo far as not to repeal them: but the Preliminaries to a Parliament are ſtill ſacred, as long as the Law ſtands that ſetled them: for the <hi>Members</hi> are ſtill in the quality of ordinary Subjects, and not entred upon their share in the Legiſlative power, till they are conſtituted in a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> legally choſen and Lawfully aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, that is, <hi>having obſerved all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites of the Law.</hi> But I leave that Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Letter</hi> to return to the moſt modeſt Apology that has been yet writ for the <hi>Dispenſing power.</hi> It yeilds that the King cannot <hi>abrogate</hi> lawes, and pretends only that he can dispenſe with them: and the diſtinction it puts between <hi>abrogation</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> is, that the one is a total repeal of the Law, and that the other is only a ſlackning of its obligatory force, with Relation to a particular man or to any body of men; ſo that according to him, a ſimple <hi>Abrogation,</hi> or a <hi>total Repeal,</hi> is beyond the compaſs of the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive I deſire then that this Doctrine may be applied to the following words of the <hi>Declaration;</hi> from which the <hi>Reader</hi> may Infer whether theſe do Import a <hi>Simple Abrogation,</hi> or not, and by Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, if the Declaration is not illegal; <hi>We do hereby further Declare, that it is our</hi> Royal will <hi>and</hi> pleaſure <hi>that the Oaths com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Oaths of Supremacy and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legeance, and alſo the ſeveral Teſts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations — shall not</hi> at any time hereafter, <hi>be required to be taken, Declared, or ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153838:6"/>by</hi> any perſon or perſons whatſoever, <hi>who is or ſhall be Imployed in any Office or Place of Truſt, either Civil or Military, under us or in our Government.</hi> This is plain <hi>English,</hi> and needs no Commentary. That paper offers likewiſe an Expedient for ſecuring <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> by which it will be ſet beyond even the <hi>Diſpenſing power;</hi> and that is, that by Act of Parliament all <hi>Perſecution</hi> may be declared to be a thing <hi>evil in it ſelf,</hi> and then the Prerogative cannot reach it. But unleſs this Author fancies, that a Parliament is that which thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> believe a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council</hi> to be, I mean <hi>Infallible,</hi> I do not ſee that ſuch an Act would ſignify any thing at all. An Act of Parliament cannot change the nature of things which are ſullen, and will not alter, becauſe a hard word is clapt on them in an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor can that make that which is not <hi>evil of it ſelf</hi> become <hi>evil of it ſelf:</hi> for can any Act of Parliament make the <hi>Clipping of Money,</hi> or the not <hi>Burying in Woollen evil of it ſelf?</hi> Such an Act were indeed <hi>null of it ſelf,</hi> and would ſink with its own weight, even without the burden of the Prerogative to preſs it down: and yet upon ſuch a ſandy foundation would theſe men have us build all our Hopes and our Securities. Another topick like this, is, that we ought to truſt to the truth of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Providence and Protection of God, and not lean ſo much to <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſts:</hi> All this were very pertinent, if God had not already given us human Aſſurances againſt the Rage of our Enemies, which we are now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to abandon, that ſo we may fall an eaſy and cheap <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to thoſe who wait for the favourable moment to <hi>deſtroy</hi> us: by the ſame reaſon they may perſuade us to take off all our <hi>Doors,</hi> or at leaſt all our <hi>Locks</hi>and <hi>Bolts,</hi> and to ſleep in this expoſed condition, truſting to Gods <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection:</hi> The ſimily may appear a little too high, tho it is really short of the matter; for we had better truſt our ſelves to all the Thieves and Robbers of the town, who would be perhaps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with a part of our <hi>Goods,</hi> then to thoſe whoſe deſigns are equally againſt both <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Body,</hi> and all that is dear to us.</p>
            <p n="12">XII. I will only add another Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the renewing of the <hi>Declaration</hi> this year, which has occaſioned the preſent ſtorm upon the <hi>Clergy.</hi> It is repeated to us that ſo we may ſee that the <hi>King</hi> continues firm to the Promiſes he made laſt year. Yet when men of honour have once given their <hi>word,</hi> they take it ill if any do not truſt to that, but muſt needs have it repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them: in the ordinary commerce of the world, the repeating of promiſes over and over again, is rather a ground of <hi>Suſpition</hi> than of <hi>Confidence:</hi> and if we judge of the accomplishment of all the other parts of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> from that one, which relates to the maintaining of the Church of England, <hi>as by Law eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed,</hi> the proceedings againſt the <hi>Fellows of Magdalen Colledge,</hi> gives us no reaſon to conclude, that this will be like <hi>the Laws of the Medes and Perſians, which alter not:</hi> all the talk of the New <hi>Magna Charta</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lay us aſleep, when we ſee ſo little regard had to the <hi>Old one.</hi> As for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity which is offered us in this repeating of the <hi>Kings</hi> promiſes, we muſt crave leave to remember, that the <hi>King of France,</hi> even after he had reſolved to break the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> of <hi>Nantes,</hi> yet repeated in above an hundred <hi>Edicts,</hi> that were reall and viſible violations of that <hi>Edict,</hi> a clauſe confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matory of the <hi>Edict of Nantes,</hi> declaring that he would never <hi>Violate</hi> it: and in that we may ſee what account is to be had of all <hi>promiſes</hi> made to <hi>Hereticks,</hi> in matters of Religion, by any Prince of the Roman Communion, but more particularly by a <hi>Prince</hi> who has put the conduct of his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> in the hands of a <hi>Jeſuite.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
